Robert H. Davis Papers
Robert H. Davis Papers
1905-1935
Davis, Robert H. (Robert Hobart), 1869-1942.
97 items (SC)
Incoming correspondence from literary figures (Zane Grey, Edgar Lee Masters, H.L. Mencken, Mary Roberts Rinehart); politicians (Fred O’Connor, James Phelan); artists (Frederick MacMonnies, Frank O. Salisbury, Herb Roth), and various notables from the turn of the century through the 1930s, most of whom Davis photographed or wrote about in his New York Sun column. Two manuscript items: a typescript ’Synopsis of the Amazing Quest of Mr. Ernest Bliss’ by E. Phillips Oppenheim, and typescript notes of a story to be called ’The Latchkey,’ attributed to A.E.W. Mason.
149197
Biographical History
Robert (Bob) Hobart Davis (1869-1942) was an American editor and photographer. He was born in Brownsville, Nebraska on March 23, 1869 to Reverend George Ransome Davis and Silvia Nichols Davis. His parents had moved from New England to Nebraska to do missionary work with the American Indians of the region. As a result, Davis was exposed to American Indian culture early-on in his childhood and even could speak a few words of Comanche, Sioux, and Cheyenne by the age of six.
Davis began his career working for this brother, Sam, to publish the Carson City Daily Appeal. Although he started by delivering the newspaper to weekly subscribers, Davis was a proficient compositor by the age of nineteen. After Carson City, Davis moved to San Francisco before moving to New York to begin work at the New York Journal. During the Spanish American War, Davis wrote about the conditions of war, his most notable work being an exposé on the rotten meat served to soldiers. Davis's first editing job was at the New York Sunday News, where he served as managing editor in early 1900s. He would go on to become editor of Munsey's Magazine, owned by Frank Munsey. While in this position Davis was known for his willingness to help young writers break into the field of literary fiction.
In addition to his editorial career, Davis was an amateur photographer. During his lifetime he took more than 3,000 portraits of a variety of prominent individuals.
Bob Davis married Madge Lee Hutchinson of San Francisco in 1899. He died in Montreal, Canada in 1942 at the age of 73.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Robert H. Davis Papers consist mainly of Incoming Correspondence from literary figures (Zane Grey, Edgar Lee Masters, H. L. Mencken, Mary Roberts Rinehart), politicians (Fred O'Connor, James Phelan), artists (Frederick MacMonnies, Herb Roth, Frank O. Salisbury), and various notables from the turn of the century through the 1930s, many of whom Davis photographed or wrote about in his New York Sun column. The Writings series contains two manuscript items: "Synopsis of the Amazing Quest of Mr. Ernest Bliss" by E. Phillips Oppenheim, and a typescript of "Notes of a Story to be Called 'The Latchkey'," attributed to A. E. W. Mason.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is divided into two series: Correspondence and Writings. The correspondence is arranged alphabetically by the correspondents' last names.
Subject and Genre Headings
Journalism; Photography; Castle, Egerton, 1858-1920.; Davis, Robert H. (Robert Hobart), 1869-1942.; Grey, Zane, 1872-1939.; MacArthur, Charles, 1895-1956.; McFee, William, 1881-1966.; MacGrath, Harold, 1871-1932.; McIntyre, O. O. (Oscar Odd), 1884-1938.; Maltby, Frances (Goggin), Mrs.; Marshall, Edison, 1894-; Masters, Edgar Lee, 1869-1950.; Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956.; Montague, Margaret Prescott, 1878-1955.; Morley, Christopher, 1890-1957.; Mulford, Clarence Edward, 1883-1956.; Nathan, George Jean, 1882-1958.; Norwood, Robert Winkworth, 1874-1932.; O’Connor, William Frederick Travers, Sir, 1870-; Oppenheim, E. Phillips (Edward Phillips), 1866-1946.; Opper, Frederick Burr, 1857-1937.; Orczy, Emmuska Orczy, Baroness, 1865-1947.; Paine, Albert Bigelow, 1861-1937.; Parker, Gilbert, 1862-1932.; Phelps, William Lyon, 1865-1943.; Phillips, Henry Wallace, 1869-1930.; Pinner, Erna, 1893-; Polk, Frank L. (Frank Lyon), 1871-1943.; Raine, William MacLeod, 1871-1954.; Rinehart, Mary Roberts, 1876-1958.; Ripley, Robert Le Roy, 1893-1949.; Robinson, Corinne Roosevelt, 1861-1933.; Roosevelt, Edith Kermit Carow, 1861-1948.; Rothafel, Samuel Lionel, d. 1936.; Salisbury, Frank O., 1874-; Sarazen, Gene.; Sitwell, Osbert, 1892-1969.; Steffens, Lincoln, 1866-1936.; Stone, Fred Andrew, 1873-; Thielen, Benedict, 1902-; Newspaper editors -- United States.; Journalists -- United States.; Photographers -- United States.; Photography -- Portraits.; Correspondence.; Journalists.; Photographers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Castle, Egerton, 10 Sep 1914 (Sc 27)
  - Grey, Zane, Mar 1931 (Sc 27)
  - MacArthur, Charles, undated (Sc 27)
  - MacFarlane, Peter Clark, 11 Oct 1915 (Sc 27)
  - McFee, William, 16 Apr 1934 (Sc 27)
  - MacGrath, Harold, undated (Sc 27)
  - McIntyre, Oscar Odd, 1930-1931; undated (Sc 27)
  - Mackay, Clarence H., 29 Jun 1926 (Sc 27)
  - MacMonnies, Frederick (and wife Alice), 1918; undated (Sc 27)
  - Maltby, Frances (Goggin), 06 Aug 1931 (Sc 27)
  - Marshall, Edison, 06 Dec 1930; undated (Sc 27)
  - Masters, Edgar Lee, Mar 1919; undated (Sc 27)
  - Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1927-1935; undated; 8 items
  - Miller, Max, undated (Sc 27)
  - Montague, Margaret Prescott, 07 Mar 1923 (Sc 27)
  - Morley, Christopher, 1929; 1932 (Sc 27)
  - Mulford, Clarence Edward, undated (Sc 27)
  - Nathan, George Jean, 09 May 1919; undated (Sc 27)
  - Norwood, Robert Winkworth, 1929; 1931 (Sc 27)
  - O'Connor, William Frederick Travers, 1932 (Sc 27)
  - Oppenheim, E. Phillips (Edward Phillips), 1914; undated (Sc 27)
  - Opper, Frederick Burr, 29 Mar 1932 (Sc 27)
  - Orczy, Emmuska Orczy, Baroness, 1914; 2 items (Sc 27)
  - Paine, Albert Bigelow, 03 Apr 1932 (Sc 27)
  - Parker, Gilbert, 1914 (Sc 27)
  - Parson, Hubert Templeton, 1928 (Sc 27)
  - Phelan, James Duval, 24 May 1919 (Sc 27)
  - Phelps, William Lyon, 1929-1934 (Sc 27)
  - Phillips, Henry Wallace, 28 Mar 1905 (Sc 27)
  - Pinner, Erna, 16 Dec 1930 (Sc 27)
  - Polk, Frank Lyon, 29 Aug 1932 (Sc 27)
  - Raine, William MacLeod, 04 Sep 1927 (Sc 27)
  - Rinehart, Mary Roberts, 1930; 1932 (Sc 27)
  - Ripley, Robert LeRoy, undated (Sc 27)
  - Robinson, Corinne Roosevelt, undated (Sc 27)
  - Roosevelt, Edith Kermit Carow, 11 Oct 1932 (Sc 27)
  - Roth, Herb, 08 Jul 1933 (Sc 27)
  - Rothafel, Samuel Lionel, 1930-1931; 3 items (Sc 27)
  - Salisbury, Frank O., [?date illegible] (Sc 27)
  - Sarazen, Gene, 15 Jun 1934 (Sc 27)
  - Shearn, Clarence John, 17 Nov 1931 (Sc 27)
  - Sitwell, Georgia (wife of Sacheverell), undated (Sc 27)
  - Sitwell, Osbert, 20 Apr 1933 (Sc 27)
  - Steffens, Lincoln, 18 Dec 1930 (Sc 27)
  - Stone, Fred Andrew, 19 Dec 1933 (Sc 27)
  - Sumner, Samuel Storrow, 18 Jul 1929 (Sc 27)
  - Thielen, Benedict, 07 Apr 1932 (Sc 27)
  - Miscellaneous unidentified, 1913-1932; undated (Sc 27)
- Writings
  - Writings by others
    - "Notes of a Story to be Called 'The Latchkey'" attributed to A. E. W. Mason, typescript (Sc 27)
    - "Synopsis of the Amazing Quest of Mr. Ernest Bliss" by E. Phillips Oppenheim, manuscript (Sc 27)